Guide to the Cushman Family Papers 1918-1985
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Cushman Family Papers
1918-1985
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 673
Cushman Family
9.4 linear feet
This collection primarily consists of the correspondence, a few diaries, limited financial records, and memorabilia of William and Clarice Cushman of Missoula, Montana, and their son, Roger Cushman. The bulk of the correspondence is letters to Clarice from her husband, William, when he was away from home in the U.S. Navy during WWII, in Liberia for four years, in the Warm Springs mental health facility in Montana, and in the Veterans Hospital in Sheridan, Wyoming. The letters chronicle the family’s daily lives, the centrality of religious beliefs, marital discord, and four decades of Clarice Cushman’s attempts to find medical and education assistance for their son, Roger Cushman, who had severe disabilities.
Biography of the Cushman Family
Clarice Mildred Stromert Cushman was born March 13, 1906 in Stratford, Iowa, to Ida and Bernard Stromert. She graduated from high school in Wilmar, Minnesota, in 1923 and from the State Teachers College in St. Cloud, Minnesota, in 1925. Clarice Stomert married William Cushman on January 12, 1935. For most of their married life Clarice Cushman lived in Missoula, Montana. She was a charter member of the Faith Evangelical Free Church.
William Howard Cushman was born January 24, 1909 in Woodstock, Ohio, to Mary Ellen and Arthur Cushman. He attended the University of Ohio, majoring in forestry, and later attended Montana State University in Missoula, Montana in 1939 and 1940. After he moved to Missoula, he worked for the U.S. Forest Service. During World War II, he served with the U.S. Navy. After the war, he worked in Liberia, Africa, for the LeTourneau Corporation for about four years. He then rejoined his family in Missoula where he did a variety of outdoors work. He was a member of the Faith Evangelical Free Church.
The Cushmans had one child, Roger, born December 10, 1938, in Missoula, Montana. Roger was diagnosed with “quadriplegia with hydrocephalus.” The Cushmans struggled with his care and education. In the mid 1940s Roger stayed at Beverly Farm Home and School for Nervous and Backward Children in Godfrey, Illinois. When that institution’s treatment was unsatisfactory, Mrs. Cushman moved with Roger to Denver, Colorado, for speech and physical therapy. By 1946 they were back in Missoula but Mrs. Cushman searched for the best options for their son for many years afterwards. Roger Cushman died February 17, 1978.
William Cushman died April 30, 1987 and Clarice Cushman died February 2, 1993, both in Missoula, Montana.
This collection is divided into four series.
Series I: Correspondence (1919-1985) The bulk of the correspondence is letters to Clarice Cushman from her husband, William Cushman, when he was away from home in the U.S. Navy during WWII, in Liberia for four years, in the Warm Springs mental health facility in Montana, and in the Veterans Hospital in Sheridan, Wyoming. The letters chronicle the family’s daily lives, the centrality of religious beliefs, marital discord, and four decades of Clarice Cushman’s attempts to find medical and education assistance for their son, Roger Cushman, who had severe disabilities. The correspondence also includes letters from relatives, friends and institutions, letters received by William Cushman, and letters received by Roger Cushman.
Series II: Diaries and Scrapbooks (1920-1971) includes Clarice Cushman’s diaries, that begin a few years before her marriage to William Cushman in 1935 and end during WWII. Her sometimes daily brief entries reveal her daily activities, social contacts, and later interactions with her husband. The more sporadic entries in William Cushman’s diaries describe his work and include one lengthier examination of his feelings about his marriage and his wife while they are apart. Clarice Cushman’s scrapbook (1920-1925) contains photos and memorabilia of her school years beginning in high school and ending when she is awarded a teaching certificate. The other two scrapbooks of local music and school events may have been done as an exercise with the Cushman’s son, Roger.
Series III: Financial Records (1928-1968) consists of a few scattered bank records and some daily and weekly income and expenditure lists.
Series IV: Miscellaneous (1918-1974) consists of memorabilia from high school, weddings, and births as well as various types of personal identification, a genealogy, church programs, and religious tracts. The few identified photos are of the Cushmans around the late 1930s.
The collection is divided into four series:
Series I: Correspondence bulk, 7.4 linear feet, 1919-1985
Subseries 1: Letters to Clarice Cushman, 6.7 linear feet, 1919-1985
Subseries 2: Letters to William Cushman, 0.5 linear feet, 1939-1973
Subseries 3: Letters to Roger Cushman, 0.2 linear feet, 1952-1958
Series II: Diaries and Scrapbooks, 1.0 linear feet, 1920-1971
Series III: Financial Records, 0.4 linear feet, 1928-1968
Series IV: Miscellaneous, 0.6 linear feet, 1918-1974
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
The Cushman Family Papers were donated to the Historical Museum of Fort Missoula in Missoula, Montana, by Althea Bell. The Museum donated the bulk of the papers to the Archives in 1998, a single letter in 2004, and three diaries in 2007.
Gift of the Historical Museum of Fort Missoula, 1998, 2004, and 2007.
Some Cushman family photographs, artifacts, and memorabilia are held by the Historic Museum of Fort Missoula in Missoula, Montana.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Cushman, Clarice Mildred Stromert, 1906-1993; Cushman, Roger, 1938-1978; Cushman, William Howard, 1909-1987
Cushman family
United States. Navy--History--World War, 1939-1945; Warm Springs State Hospital
Americans--Liberia--Correspondence; Children with disabilities--Montana--Missoula; Parents of children with disabilities--Montana--Missoula; Psychiatric hospitals--Montana; Veterans' hospitals--Wyoming--Sheridan; Women--Montana--Missoula--Diaries; World War, 1939-1945--Personal narratives, American
Diaries--Montana--Missoula; Scrapbooks--Montana--Missoula
Mental Health; Scrapbooks; Missoula; Montana
- Correspondence, 1919-1985; Series I; 7.4 linear feet
  - Letters to Clarice Cushman, 1919-1985; Subseries 1; 6.7 linear feet
    - Letters from aunt, 1919 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Letters from mother and friends, 1923 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Letters from sister and friends, 1924 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Letters from sister, 1925 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Letters from mother, sister, and friends, 1926 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1927 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Letters from sister and friends, 1928 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Letters from mother, sister, and friends, 1929 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, ca. 1920s (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Letters from mother and sister, 1930 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Letters from friends, 1930 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Letters from mother, sister, and friends, 1931 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Letters from mother, sister, and friends, 1932 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Letters from sister and friends, 1933 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Letters from sister and William (Bill) Cushman, Jan-Sept 1934 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Letters from friends and William Cushman, Oct-Dec1934 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Letters from husband and sister, 1935 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Letters from husband, mother, and sister, 1936 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, Jan-June 1937 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, June-Dec 1937 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, Jan-Mar 1938 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, June-Dec 1938 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, Jan-May 1939 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, June-Dec 1939 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, circa 1930s (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, Jan-May 1940 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, June-Sept 1940 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, Oct-Dec 1940 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1940 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, friends, and church leaders, 1941 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, 1942 (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Letters from relatives, friends, and lawyer, 1943 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Letters from husband, Aug-Sept 1943 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Letters from husband, Oct-Dec 1943 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Letters from institutions regarding possible placement of Roger Cushman, 1943 (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Letters from husband, Jan-June 1944 (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Letters from husband, July-Aug 1944 (Box-folder 6/3)
    - Letters from husband, Sept-Oct 1944 (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Letters from husband, Nov-Dec 1944 (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1944 (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Letters from institutions, 1944 (Box-folder 7/2)
    - Letters from husband, Jan-Feb 1945 (Box-folder 7/3)
    - Letters from husband, Feb-Mar 1945 (Box-folder 7/4)
    - Letters from husband, Apr-June 1945 (Box-folder 7/5)
    - Letters from husband, July-Oct 1945 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1945 (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Letters from institutions, 1945 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1946 (Box-folder 8/4)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1947 (Box-folder 8/5)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1948 (Box-folder 8/6)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, 1949 (Box-folder 9/1)
    - Letters from institutions and others regarding Roger Cushman, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 9/2)
    - Letters from husband, ca. 1940s (Box-folder 9/3)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, ca. 1940s (Box-folder 9/4)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, 1950 (Box-folder 9/5)
    - Letters from husband, 1951 (Box-folder 9/6)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1951 (Box-folder 9/7)
    - Letters from husband, Jan-Mar 1952 (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Letters from husband, Apr-June 1952 (Box-folder 10/2)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1952 (Box-folder 10/3)
    - Letters from institutions, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 10/4)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1953 (Box-folder 10/5)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1954 (Box-folder 10/6)
    - Letters from institutions, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 11/1)
    - Letters from husband, 1955 (Box-folder 11/2)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1955 (Box-folder 11/3)
    - Letters from husband, 1956 (Box-folder 11/4)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1956 (Box-folder 11/5)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, 1957 (Box-folder 11/6)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1958 (Box-folder 11/7)
    - Letters from husband, 1959 (Box-folder 11/8)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1959 (Box-folder 12/1)
    - Letters from husband, ca. 1950s (Box-folder 12/2)
    - Letters from husband, 1960 (Box-folder 12/3)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1960 (Box-folder 12/4)
    - Letters from husband, 1961 (Box-folder 12/5)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1961 (Box-folder 12/6)
    - Letters from institutions, 1961 (Box-folder 13/1)
    - Letters from husband, relatives, and friends, 1962 (Box-folder 13/2)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1963-1968 (Box-folder 13/3)
    - Letters from institutions, 1963-1966 (Box-folder 13/4)
    - Letter from relative and religious literature, ca. 1960s (Box-folder 13/5)
    - Letters from institutions, ca. 1960s (Box-folder 13/6)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1970-1979 (Box-folder 13/7)
    - Letters from institutions, 1970-1978 (Box-folder 13/8)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 13/9)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, undated (Box-folder 14/1)
    - Holiday Greeting Cards, undated (Box-folder 14/2)
  - Letters to William Cushman, 1939-1973; Subseries 2; 0.5 linear feet
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1939 (Box-folder 14/3)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1940-1943 (Box-folder 14/4)
    - Letters from wife, May 1941-Apr 1944 (Box-folder 14/5)
    - Letters from wife, May 1944-Oct 1945 (Box-folder 14/6)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1944-1949 (Box-folder 15/1)
    - Letters from relatives and friends, 1950-1973 (Box-folder 15/2)
    - Letters and drawings regarding inventions, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 15/3)
    - Letters and greeting cards from wife, undated (Box-folder 15/4)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, undated (Box-folder 15/5)
  - Letters to Roger Cushman, 1952-1958; Subseries 3; 0.2 linear feet
    - Letters from father, relatives, and friends, 1952-1958 (Box-folder 15/6)
    - Letters and other materials regarding Roger, undated (Box-folder 15/7)
- Diaries and scrapbooks, 1920-1971; Series II; 1.0 linear foot
  - Clarice Cushman’s diary, 1934-1938 (Box-folder 15/8)
  - Clarice Cushman’s diary, 1939-1943 (Box-folder 16/1)
  - William Cushman’s diary, 1943-1956 (Box-folder 16/2)
  - William Cushman’s diary, ca. 1944 (Box-folder 16/3)
  - Clarice Cushman scrapbook, 1920-1925 (Box-folder 16/6)
  - Scrapbook of local concerts and school events, 1969-1970 (Box-folder OS 1)
  - Scrapbook of local concerts and school events, 1970-1971 (Box-folder OS 1)
- Financial Records, 1928-1968; Series III; 0.4 linear feet
  - Minnesota Building and Loan passbook, 1928-1936 (Box-folder 16/7)
  - Bank statement, 1934 (Box-folder 16/8)
  - Bank statement, 1957 (Box-folder 16/9)
  - Western Montana Clinic, 1940-1943 (Box-folder 16/10)
  - Financial records, 1948-1950 (Box-folder 16/11)
  - Financial records, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 17/1)
  - Financial records, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 17/2)
  - Financial records, 1961-1968 (Box-folder 17/3)
- Miscellaneous, 1918-1978; Series IV; 0.6 linear feet
  - Clarice Cushman’s graduation announcements and commencement programs, 1923 (Box-folder 17/4)
  - Edna Margaret Stomert’s wedding announcement, 1924 (Box-folder 17/5)
  - Clarice Cushman’s State Teacher’s College Graduation announcement, 1925 (Box-folder 17/6)
  - Clarice Cushman’s Montana State Teaching Certificate, 1932 (Box-folder 17/7)
  - Photos of Clarice, William, and Roger, ca. 1939 (Box-folder 17/8)
  - Unidentified photos, undated (Box-folder 17/9)
  - William Cushman’s MSU Student Handbook with his student transcripts attached, 1937-1940 (Box-folder 17/10)
  - Baby cards and gift tags, 1938 (Box-folder 17/11)
  - Draft card, passport, driver’s licenses, and other, 1940-1960 (Box-folder 17/12)
  - Clarice Cushman’s handwritten list of news stories, undated (Box-folder 17/13)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box-folder 18/1)
  - Cushman genealogy, 1978 (Box-folder 18/2)
  - Clarice Cushman’s Willmar High School monthly magazine, 1918 (Box-folder 18/3)
  - Clarice Cushman’s Willmar High School senior yearbook, 1923 (Box-folder 18/4)
  - Miscellaneous research, undated (Box-folder 18/5)
  - Church programs, 1944 (Box-folder 18/6)
  - Religious tracts, music programs, and travel information, undated (Box-folder 18/7)